<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to a scandalous and deceitfull pamphlet: entituled, Considerable queries humbly tendred touching reducement of the excise to the customs; published by necessity.</title>
            <author>Wattes, Jeremiah.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B10272</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 80925382</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1153A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R186315</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">80925382</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 80925382</idno>
            <idno type="VID">192174</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B10272)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 192174)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2901:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to a scandalous and deceitfull pamphlet: entituled, Considerable queries humbly tendred touching reducement of the excise to the customs; published by necessity.</title>
                  <author>Wattes, Jeremiah.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed: Jeremiah Wattes.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Considerable queries humbly tendred touching reducement of the excise to the customs.</term>
               <term>Excise tax --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:192174:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:192174:1"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO A Scandalous and Deceitfull Pamphlet: ENTITULED, <hi>Conſiderable Queries humbly tendred touching Reducement of the Exciſe to the Cuſtoms; Publiſhed by</hi> Neceſſity.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y a lover of truth, and diſcoverer of fawning cringing companions, who having little wit and much confidence; a large proportion of ignorance in affaires they entermedle with; blinded with deſire of Gain, and large Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, pretend the <hi>Common-wealths</hi> good, while they only aime to inrich themſelves, and by baſe flatteries, love lobby attendances, and other ſneaking applications; thinke by fair words to deceive men into a good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of themſelves, and would make men beleeve they are neceſſitated to confirme them in their imployments, or transfer them to better places, where money is ſtirring and gain coming in, and then their worke is done: whether the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:192174:2"/>worke of the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> be done or undone, ſink or ſwim. Which preſumptuous boldneſſe, and immodeſt cariage, proceeds from a hope they have upon Unkles, or Cozens in the Parliament, as <hi>Neceſſity</hi> who had a Kinſman by his endeavours ſo powerfull as to make a thin Lawyer, and ſlender Souldiers, inſtantly became a ſound, ſubſtantiall experienced Exciſe man, and a Cozen Commiſſioner, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he ſcarce knew Straw from Hoppes, or Sattin from Buckram, as if there was a communicative power by the laying on of his Kinſmans hands, to ordain him and infuſe new principles of underſtanding; and in an inſtant to make him know the myſteries of all Trade, and Commerce, the kinds, values, and denominations of all Goods and Merchandize, and to indue him with qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations that might fit him to purſe up money ſufficient for himſelf and Ordinary, and yet all this to be accounted no fimony.</p>
            <p>It is almoſt to be wondered, that the influence of a <hi>malevolent</hi> Planet whoſe motion is ſo near the earth, by his favorable aſpect ſhould have ſuch operation on ſo dull a body: That he who had not the audacity to come within a mile of a Corporation where Bayliffs held juriſdiction, ſhould now be ſo preſumptuouſly bold to take upon him to Exciſe and Judge the people, conceiting that the world is not governed by ſo much wiſdome, as many Sage men have thought; and being thus ſteeld, dare openly appear at the Parliament door, ſetting forth ſelf in Print, yea printing himſelf a conſiderable fellow; yea more, that the Brats of his own braines lately wet and ſqueeſed, are ſo conſderable as to be fit for the guidance of the Parliament. By this it's apparent how little braines and great Salaries worke together; but ſuch perſons I hope will be ſoon eſpied and rejected; eſpecially ſuch, as being intruſted and impolyed by the Parliament, and think it no crime to be ignorant and neglectfull of their own duty, and upbraid and ſcandalize thoſe that are knowing and diligent in their truſt, ſhall not onely be
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:192174:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>judged unfit for any other imployment, but as unprofitable and unfaithfull ſervants be thruſt out, and wiſer and honeſter men imployed in their rooms. Such men make a duſt, leſt their want of ability ſhould be diſcerned; and puddle the waters, that you may not ſee the ſhallowneſſe of their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and how inconſiderately they manage the truſt repoſed in them; like Lapwings to draw you from their neſt, make moſt noyſe where there is leaſt cauſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 1. He ſaith the receipt of the Exciſe is 300000 <hi>l. per an.</hi> notwithſtanding the great obſtructions, and is dayly increaſing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There will, and needs muſt be great obſtructions, whilſt men of no better abilities and inſight into Trade, have the management thereof; for what can be expected from men that know nothing of regulating matters of Commerce and Trade? Merchants and Traders that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand all the wayes, and by-wayes of Trade, will eaſily out-wit ignoramuſſes, and inferiour officers can eaſily ſee their Mr. Commiſſioners ignorance, and although in words they applaud him, yet may play their games with the Merchants, and other Traders to their advantage, whileſt ſuch a Commiſſioner is blinded with a notion of his deſerving into that he never knew nor under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood.</p>
            <p>And for the dayly increaſe of that revenue; I cannot but wonder at the ignorance of the Author, for many years paſt, when warres were in the Land, and the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament had not the whole Nation under their power, yet the Exciſe was then about 400000. l. and now it is about 300000. <hi>l. per an.</hi> this is the growing receipt like a Cowes tail downwards.</p>
            <p>It's true for two years laſt paſt, ſome ſeeming ſmall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement hath been in the receipt of the Exciſe, but if the ſame be examined it will appear to be only by farming it out, whereby the people have been moſt miſerably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted upon and oppreſt, not only by a due taking the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:192174:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>utmoſt for Exciſe of Commodities, but alſo forcing Inn-keepers and others to pay an Annuall ſum for above what their Annual Exciſe would come to, or elſe by the frowns and favours of them or their unreaſonable farmers, to put them into a worſe condition by fines and ſeizures of their goods; procuring Licenſes for Alehouſes to be taken on their owne termes, or if the parties conſent not they are ſuppreſt, and a number ſuch ſhirking trickes, grievous to the people. All which I hope the Parliament will not only reforme, but alſo puniſh the Authors of ſuch exorbitances.</p>
            <p>It is true as <hi>Neceſſity</hi> ſaith, the Receipt of the Cuſtomes is a vaſt receipt, and he might have ſaid a growing receipt, for it hath advanced under the Management of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Commiſſioners. That in every one of theſe foure laſt yeares they have accompted for between three and four hundred thouſand pound <hi>per an.</hi> although in every one of theſe years, ſuch hinderances have happened, that have much prejudiced that Receipt, as in former years have not been known. As firſt, the prohibition of French Wine, which if imported as formerly would have added 40000. <hi>l. per an.</hi> to the receipt. The Portugal Trade about 30000. <hi>l. per an.</hi> The Levant and Turky Trade, about 40000. <hi>l. per an.</hi> The Barbadoes and other American Trade about 30000. <hi>l. per an.</hi> all of which have been wanting to the receipt of Cuſtomes, in ſome of thoſe years, and ſome of the moſt conſiderable of them wanting ſtill. And although the trade of Portugall be come into the receipt of late, yet not in that proportion as was heretofore. The trade of Barbadoes and other Iſlands are now added to the receipt; yet there wants the trades of Muſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via, Holland, and the eaſt Country, whereby it is much leſſe then otherwiſe it would be; as alſo, the French, Levant and Turkey trade, are loſt to that receipt.</p>
            <p>Undoubtedly if ſuch a free trade were now in <hi>England,</hi> as was in <hi>Anno</hi> 1648. or any year before, the receipt of the Cuſtomes would riſe to 500000. <hi>l. per an.</hi> if mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:192174:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>with the ſame or the like judgement, care, skill, and induſtry, they now are by the preſent Commiſſioners and officers.</p>
            <p>In the ſame Page <hi>Neceſſity</hi> further ſaith, the Exciſe is a full check to the Cuſtome, and the Cuſtomes a full check to the Exciſe; if ignorance were not the mother of this, he would never have publiſhed; there ſits an honourable Gentleman in Parliament, who is one of the checks to the Cuſtomes, and can informe how true this aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is.</p>
            <p>But if the Cuſtomes be a full check to the Exciſe, why is not that receipt bettered by that check of the Cuſtomes? For it is evident that of thoſe Commodities imported, which are moſt unlikely to be conveighed away without payment of Cuſtome and Exciſe, the Commiſſioners of the Cuſtomes do Annually receive above double as much money as the Commiſſioners of Exciſe for the ſame Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, due regard in this calculation being had as well to the values ſet, or taken for the ſaid goods on the duties payable to the reſpective receipts, as alſo deduction for any of them exported.</p>
            <p>And ſince <hi>Neceſſity</hi> aſſerts from his own mouth, that the Exciſe is a full check to the Cuſtomes, and the Cuſtomes to the Exciſe; why then ſhould not the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament (I hope they will on <hi>Englands</hi> behalfe) command both the Commiſſioners of the Cuſtomes, and Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners of Exciſe, to give in their ſeverall accompts perfect, for what hath been collected for every diſtinct kinde and ſort of goods imported, and if either of them have been deficient, that they will ſee the Common-wealth righted, out of the eſtates of ſuch as are culpable?</p>
            <p>And this ſeems but juſt in reſpect each ſet of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners have conſiderable Salaries, <hi>viz.</hi> the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Cuſtoms 4 d. in the pound for their Salarie, and for ſecuring to the Common-wealth the whole receipt of the Cuſtomes every 24 day of <hi>June,</hi> how much ſoever ſtands
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:192174:4"/>out unreceived, or is loſt by the inſolvency or non-perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of any Collector, as alſo to forbeare all manner of trade as Merchants, and to pay out of the ſaid 4 <hi>d. per l.</hi> ſome additionall Clerks, and to ſatisfie the incident charges expended for the better management of that affair, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by the Contract betwixt the late Parliament, and the preſent Commiſſioners of Cuſtomes, extant in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of Parliament.</p>
            <p>And the Commiſſioners of Exciſe have 3 <hi>d.</hi> in the pound for their Salarie, without any ingagement for debts, or incident charges.</p>
            <p>The leaſt of which Salaries is a ſufficient reward and conſideration either to the aforeſaid accompt or ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
            <p>There is an old proverb, whem Gameſters fall out true men come by their goods; and <hi>Neceſſity</hi> hath put me upon the diſcovery of ſuch ajuſt experiment, as may deter weak unskilfull men from their bold attempts, for the ſame or like places of profit. And as it's fit to recompenſe men of parts and abilities, that ſerve the Common-wealth well, and profitably, ſo it is juſt to puniſh ſuch as dare take upon them publick truſt, without skill, or ability, to manage the ſame ſutably to the duty incumbent on them.</p>
            <p>It's man-like to beat a quarreller with his own weapon, the ſay <hi>Neceſſity</hi> will make a man fight, and it will not be amiſſe to turne the miſchief he intends to others upon his owne pate, that ſo he may do no more hurt with his penne, then he could formerly doe with his Pike.</p>
            <p>Some men are opinionated they are fit for every im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, able to undertake any buſineſſe, and would have others beleeve them to be the only uſeful men in peace and warre.</p>
            <p>And when men of parts after long experience, great travell, and diligent ſtudy, with much heſitation, are hardly perſwaded to take a command, or any other im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:192174:4"/>of charge, doubting their ſufficiency, you ſhall have a confident pettifogger turn his buckram bag into a ſnapſack, and inſtantly become a Colonell, and Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of a garriſon, where he may have little to do, and lie far enough from his enemy, &amp; never attempt any thing wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the name of a Souldier; yet there is neceſſity he be paid as well as he hath hazards his life daily. And when the wars are done, at firſt daſh can have wit enough, with help of friends, to be a Commiſſioner of Exciſe, although a place that would require more ſolidity, &amp; better experience then he could finde either in his ſnapſack, or buckram bag; yet is ſo bold to put himſelf in print, and thinks all mens underſtandings are ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low as his own, and hopes to raiſe ſo much mud at the Cuſtome-houſe, that you ſhall never ſee what water runs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the mill at the Exciſe: pag. 1. he aſſerts the Receipt of the Exciſe annually to be 300000 <hi>l.</hi> and pag. 3. he ſaith the annuall Receit of native Commodities to be 150000 <hi>l.</hi> then it muſt follow that the Receipt of imported goods, is the other moity and but 150000 l. And I do not beleeve up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on examination it will appear to be ſo much, and that the Receipt of the Cuſtomes for the ſame is double as much. And yet the charge of collecting the Exciſe, is much more as he confeſſes, pag. 1. to be about 2 <hi>s</hi> in the pound, which he calculateth upon the whole Receipt of Exciſe; as well for goods imported as for native commodities: the laſt of which were for the moſt part farmed, and ſo bring no charge, except 3 <hi>d. per l.</hi> to the Commiſſioners. And if <hi>Neceſsity</hi> underſtood the buſineſſe of the exciſe, he might have told you, that the ſums of money raiſed by farming the Exciſe without charge by the pound, other then is aforeſaid, being deducted from the ſum collected for goods imported, and other native goods not farmed, and the whole charge of officers, and other incident charges being proportioned, as in right it ought to be at the latter end of the charge of collecting the Exciſe, doth amount unto about 3 <hi>s.</hi> 8 <hi>d.</hi> or 4 <hi>s</hi> in the pound, for goods imported, but when gain is the end, miſts and dark clouds are the way.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:192174:5"/>
            <p>I obſerved before that <hi>Neceſſity</hi> concludes the Exciſe, a full check to the Cuſtomes, as they now ſtand, and yet within four or five lines, he ſaith it was once a perfect Check: I would gladly know by what <hi>Logick,</hi> he can diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween full and perfect, in that ſenſe wherein they are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed.</p>
            <p>In the end of the 1. pag. he ſaith the Officers of Exciſe formerly put aboard ſhips, and at water ſide, were taken off by the Committee of Regulation of Exciſe: which, he ſaith, was done to ſave charges, and the iſſue of it is, that few rich goods are entred either in Exciſe or Cuſtomes, and both du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties loſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Officers of Exciſe on ſhip-board and at water ſide were a great Charge to the State, and thoſe aboard were a great grievance to the owners of ſhipping lying there at their charge for meat and drink, and no benefit at all, for they only joyned with the Officers of the Cuſtomes on board to take the numbers and marks and outward formes of goods and come along with the Lighters to the Keyes: but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were ſilk or thrums, full or empty, they knew not; and ſuch officers were very like to make <hi>Neceſſities</hi> full Check to become a perfect Check; whereas nothing could come as perfect from the Tideſmen, but muſt be expected from the Land-waiter, the main and chief end of Tideſmen being aboard is to prevent any goods fromm being delivered without due entry.</p>
            <p>But it is apparently known, that what through the meanneſſe of the ſalary thoſe tideſmen had, and what through want of care and conſcience, not only in the chief Officers in chooſing them, and the behaviour of theſe tideſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, they truſting to the Officers of the Cuſtomes, and the Officers of Cuſtomes truſting to them: it did plainly appear they were more burthenſome then profitable, for Mr. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel Moyer</hi> and others ſitting in <hi>Mincing Lane London,</hi> autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſed for regulating the Officers, and management of the Cuſtomes, gave it as their opinion, that thenceforth all the Officers of Exciſe imployed on ſhipboard, and at the water
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:192174:5"/>ſide, ſhould be diſmiſſed; and that the ſole management for importation, exportation, and tranſportation, ſhould be in the Commiſſioners of Cuſtomes and their Officers. And it was ordered accordingly: by which diſmiſſion the Common-wealth ſaved a large ſum of money Annually.</p>
            <p>Since which time the Cuſtomes have been advanced to (neer or altogether) double what they then were. And yet there is no entry for landing goods paſſed by the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners of Cuſtomes, untill the Deputy of the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Exciſe do certifie that they are ſatisfied for the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe due thereupon; and yet <hi>Neceſſity</hi> ſaith the Cuſtome is loſt and Exciſe too. That the cuſtome is not loſt appears by the advance thereof: but that the Exciſe is loſt appears is manifeſt by the declenſion of that Receipt, whileſt the Deputy for Exciſe certifies he is ſatisfied, and <hi>Neceſſity</hi> ſaith it is not paid.</p>
            <p>It's manifeſt then how he manages the Exciſe; heretofore one of the ableſt of the old Commiſſioners, did ſit in the Exciſe Office at the water ſide, but of late no ſuch thing. And indeed it matters not, if there be no wiſer among them then <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> who could not tell what to do, if he were there. And therefore pag. 2. he ſaith, <hi>Attendance at the Cuſtome houſe is the leaſt work of the Exciſe Office.</hi> And ſo the work too mean for a man of his worth: whereas it's known to all experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced men, that it is the very key of the work, and the foundation for a true Receipt, for Goods inported, and as this is well or ill done, ſo it ſaveth or loſeth the duty; for by this they can oly call men to accompt, and compell pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for goods imported when they are ſold.</p>
            <p>It's manifeſt that the decay of Exciſe is the deceiving the Common-wealth; for if the Cuſtome be paid and due entry made, and the entry certified by the Exciſe Officers, that they are ſatisfied for Exciſe, it will be no hard matter to finde where the fault is. And I dare affirme, if the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will pleaſe to command an accompt of the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners both of Cuſtomes and Exciſe as aforeſaid, it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that <hi>Neceſsity</hi> doth not well (or knowes not how to)
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:192174:6"/>manage ſuch a Receipt: and therefore he is troubled, that any wiſer then himſelf are imployed in publique Receipts, as appears in the bottome of his firſt pag. where ſpeaking of the Committee for Regulating the Exciſe, he writes (not prints) <hi>Colonell</hi> Harvey <hi>one of the Commiſsioners for the Cuſtomes was a powerfull Member.</hi> For my part I conceive it was well for the Common-wealth he was a Member of that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee, and a Commiſſioner of the Cuſtomes; for all that know him do know him to be experienced in all manner of Traffique, and Commerce, of a quick underſtanding, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious, and excellent in diſpatch of buſineſſe, and I hope truly honeſt; one made up with qualifications fit for a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Receipt. I might ſay more, and God knowes I flatter not, but ſpeak what I know, and <hi>Neceſſity</hi> conſtrained me to ſay ſomething, becauſe he is named ſo emphatically with <hi>Neceſsities</hi> own hand-writing (if I miſtake not) but whether to commend or defame him I know not, he comes off ſo ſneakingly.</p>
            <p>The reſt of his Pamphlet is ſtuffed with ſuch reaſon as he can deviſe to ſhew his fear, leſt the Exciſe be brought to the Cuſtomes, and managed by one and the ſame number of perſons, and this alteration he knowes may undoe him, and therefore is in a bodily fear, not having a friend in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to cover his black head with a white lock, and is like to want that fine dreſſe of commendations whereby he was ſo well ſet out by his Unkle, that he became one of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments darlings, and an Officer in ſo great a truſt. And therefore now laies about him, throwes dirt in ſome mens faces, frowns on others, growes ſawcy with his Maſters, ſwels high in his own imagination, offers the example of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Leghorne,</hi> to abate the ancient and ſolid revenue of the Cuſtomes, and to inhaunce the new (and it is hoped not intended to be long continued) Receipt of the Exciſe, as p. 4. which laſt was ſet on foot only in times of extremity and expected to ceaſe when the preſſing occaſions of the Nation will permit. I cannot eaſily paſſe by his argument, to expell pride, luxury, and drunkenneſſe, by making proud, luxuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:192174:6"/>drunken perſons pay more for their ſinnes.</p>
            <p>If the man did but know what neceſſity he hath to ſtudy his own buſineſſe, for which he is ſo well (if not too well) paid, he might be able out of his own experience to tell others, that Wines and ſilk were never known ſo dear as of late times, and is there any leſſe will or deſire to the exceſſive uſe of either? And doth not daily experience manifeſt, that drunkards will have drink, ſet what rate you will upon it: and are there not many that can hardly get 7 <hi>s.</hi> a week by hard labour, that will ſpend 4, or 5 <hi>s.</hi> in a day though wife and children ſtarve at home? <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaies, a rod for he fools back, it's not pecuniary mulcts, but corporall puniſhment that muſt deter men from ſuch ſins.</p>
            <p>I do not a little wonder that any dares in a Chriſtian Common-wealth propound ſuch a motion, as if we ſhould imitate the whoriſh Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> who allowes common Stewes becauſe they fill the Popes coffers and ſo increaſe their treaſure with the hire of a Whore, or as the Ruſſian, when reproved for drunkenneſſe, replies, Oh its good for my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the Emperour, he being the great Merchant of Strong-Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and cares not to puniſh that ſin becauſe it brings in profit. But I hope there will be no Neceſſity to plead againſt ſuch abominable gain, for you ſhall finde him in the lower end of that page, talk a little goodiſh, he ſpeaks of reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but it's not a throughout reforming he aimes at, (the Exciſe are perfect already) but it's to paſſe upon the Cuſtome Officers before ſuch reducement.</p>
            <p>If it were good for the Common-wealth to make any ſuch reducement, (as in my opinion it is not, but more for the publick advantage to keep the Receipts apart) good reaſon might be for ſome variation of Salaries: but I know that is not his drift to obſerve, nor mine to reply; yet let me tell him, that the ſalaries that now are, were ſetled to the Officers of the Cuſtomes upon very great judgement, and prepared, and propoſed by perſons of unqueſtionable abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, skill and experience, honeſty and good affection, <hi>viz.</hi> The Committee of Merchants then ſitting in <hi>Mincing Lane,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:192174:7"/>authoriſed thereunto by Act of Parliament, <hi>Anno</hi> 1648, ad 49. of which Mr. <hi>Samuel Moyer,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Richard Hutchinſon</hi> were two, with many other choice and ſelect perſons, who firſt preſented them unto the Committee of the Navie and Cuſtomes, who reported the matter to the Parliament then ſitting, and was by them confirmed: and dares he blunder out queſtions whether it be fit or unfit? And then from quarrelling at their ſalaries, he fals upon their perſons, and in generall termes, charges many with trading as Merchants and Factors, and indefinitly accuſes all with obſtructing the Exciſe, violation of truſt, concealing and defrauding the State their dues.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſſe it was a more then ordinary paſſion that urged <hi>Neceſſity</hi> thus to lay about him and ſpare none: Why man, is there never an honeſt man at Cuſtome houſe, not Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Titchbourne,</hi> nor Mr. <hi>Samuel Moyer?</hi> you made a criticall diſtinction betwixt full and perfect: why are you now ſo indefinite, ſure you never obſerved that rule in Logick, that every indefinite propoſition muſt be conſtrued univerſally; and if ſo, thou haſt then comprehended them with the reſt. But I dare undertake you did it unwittingly, or without wit, otherwiſe you would never have adventured to run the hazard of their diſpleaſure, and go againſt a known rule to ſpeak evill of dignities, but you may hope they have greater buſineſſe then to trouble themſelves with a — whoſe tongue is no ſlander, and ſo forgive, though I know not how they can forget becauſe you have given them a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance in print.</p>
            <p>Had it not been better policy to have hid your ſelf behinde your large ſalary and vaſt ignorance, and have bleſſed your ſelf; you were ſo inconſiderable as not to be thought on, theſe being not times for men of poor parts and rich places to be rampant, when they have to doe with an Eagle-eyed State.</p>
            <p>You ſay many of the Cuſtome Officers trade as Factors, it's ſtrange you can name none but one long ſince thrown out of his imployment; it's not ſaying but proving they trade,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:192174:7"/>that makes them puniſhable. And amongſt the many crimes you lay to their charge in defrauding the Exciſe, you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance only a caſe near two years ſince of one <hi>Opye</hi> of <hi>Plimouth,</hi> who was detected and caſt out of his Collectors place, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he had many friends in the Parliament, and divers eminent Officers of the Army, applyed in his behalfe to the Commiſſioners of Cuſtomes, yet ſo juſt and unbyaſſed were they to their truſt, that no courtſhip could prevail with them.</p>
            <p>I could tell you of many more in the port of <hi>London,</hi> and elſewhere, whom they have caſt out for the like offences, and it might have had ſome ſeeming ſhew of honeſty if you had named any at preſent in imployment that had been guilty, which the Commiſſioners have winked at: nay I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident that upon the exacteſt inquiry it will not be found that they ever indulged any proved guilty of this or the like miſdemeanors, either in his place or converſation. And truely I conceive if you knew any ſuch thing by any Officer, there lay a Neceſſity upon you to have diſcovered it to the Commiſſioners of Cuſtome, wherein you could not have failed of a fair acceptance, and a due proceeding againſt the offender according to juſtice.</p>
            <p>Although <hi>Neceſſity</hi> have no law, yet he might have had ſome modeſt ſhame, every ingenuous man will ſay theſe are unhandſome, illegall, unchariſtian like proceedings; and that you rather intend to calumniate then reforme: I wiſh the Parliament would inforce you to make good your charge, and if you do not, I ſhall be inforced to ſay <hi>Neceſſity</hi> hath no honeſty. And in this <hi>Neceſſity</hi> hath ſhewed himſelf a very buſibody, quick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ighted abroad but dull at home; he can ſpie a moat at Cuſtome houſe, and ſees not a beam at the Exciſe, you might have reckoned divers amongſt your Commiſſioners and Officers that keep their trades, and deal in many Exciſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble commodities, did Mr. <hi>Morice Thomſon,</hi> M. <hi>Boner,</hi> Mr. <hi>Thomas Lentall,</hi> with others, as alſo divers inferior Officers give over their trades?</p>
            <p>And is there not the like order of Parliament againſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:192174:8"/>Exciſe officers trading in Commodities Exciſeable? is not this thy complaining upon others and neglecting reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at home, baſe hypocriſie? doth not this render thee one that keeps not company with a good conſcience and underſtanding? &amp; doth not thy affirming many to be guilty, and particularly naming but one (and he long ſince thrown out of his imployment) throw dirt in the face of all, even Commiſſioners, Clerks, and al other Officers? And yet I am of opinion, that in your own conſcience you acquit every one in the port of <hi>London,</hi> and know not any thing of guilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe elſewhere: yet with an impudent face you charge the Officers with concealing goods Exciſeable, and defrauding the Exciſe, due upon conviction of offenders for non entry of goods.</p>
            <p>It is true, the Exciſe may not be paid, but it's through your own negligence, or ignorance, or unfaithfulneſſe, and it ſeems you bring not ſuch ſums to accompt; but I ſhall tell you, and make it good, that the Commiſſioners of Cuſtomes cauſe all goods ſeized, to be brought into the Common-wealths warehouſe, and the Exciſe officers are acquainted with them; whence they are not delivered before compoſition, or condemnation, or order of Parliament, nor before due entrie be made of the ſame, and Cuſtome paid and certified to be ſatisfied for Exciſe by your hand and eyes, indeed your skill, wiſdome and experience, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Tho. Lenthall</hi> and Mr. <hi>Jo. Crue.</hi> And of theſe as alſo for all other goods have the Commiſſioners of Cuſtomes ſuch Certificates and fair accompt kept thereof, that when this ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired into, as I hope it will, and am aſſured you know will be proved; I wiſh you be able to anſwer the Common-wealth for the ſums that they will prove you have certified to have received: and yet you now aſſert you have not, but that they are loſt to the Receipt. Beleeve me, they that have found them, or kept them back, or concealed them from the Common-wealth, it's juſt they ſhould be compelled to vomit them up again.</p>
            <p>Well <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> I perceive you can play the Orator (or he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:192174:8"/>that compriſed the Book, did it for you) to end higheſt at laſt: pag. 5. &amp; 6. You fall upon the Commiſſioners themſelves, yet have learned ſo much wit in your anger as to charge but ſome of them [and then it followes in written hand] <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners for Customes,</hi> viz. Col. <hi>Harvy,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hildersly, and</hi> Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> have themſelves ſtrongly obſtructed the receipt of the Exciſe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Pray, what <hi>Neceſſity</hi> was there to charge three Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners and not the other, <hi>viz.</hi> Alderman <hi>Tichborne?</hi> I dare aſſure you no Act was ever done in order to the management of the Cuſtomes, but by and with conſent and concurrence of the whole or major part, although it may be ſigned or pronounced by one for orders ſake; they Regiſter all their proceedings, and can give an account out of their diaries of all they ever did as Commiſſioners: I wiſh you did ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the like order, for your own and the Common-wealths ſake. The reaſon then is plain, that the whole drift of your Pamphlet reports it fawning and ſcraping to be continued in your office, and are affraid to name Alderman <hi>Titchborne</hi> being a member of Parliament.</p>
            <p>But you can mildly take your fellow ſervants by the throat of their reputation, and falſly accuſe them unto their maſters; having herein neither as a wiſe man or a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an well informed your ſelf, nor conſidered with them for ſatisfaction, information, or reformation as it ought to be done. But as the love of money is the root of all evill, ſo it is the root of that evill; will you ſhew againſt your brethren, the fear of loſſe of your gainfull trade makes you imitate <hi>Demetrius</hi> and his <hi>Copperſmiths,</hi> they cry up the greatneſſe of their Goddeſſe, and make a tumult and would ſeem devout obſervers of that deity, and inrages the people againſt the Apoſtles; But that which troubled them, was, leſt he ſhould loſe his gainful occupation: ſo your jealouſie leſt your craft ſhould fail, and your gain leſſen, hath put you upon this unchriſtian, uncharitable behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, ſo diſhoneſtly to beſpatter theſe wourthy, religious and Godly perſons.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:192174:9"/>
            <p>Could you not conſider they were too well known for you to get any Credence by a bare generall accuſation.</p>
            <p>All men of any eminent trade and buſineſſe knows, Coll. <hi>Harvy,</hi> who never obſcurely lived being borne &amp; bred in the City, had a conſiderable eſtate left him, and when he traded as a Silk-man or Merchant, had one of the greateſt trades in <hi>London,</hi> had the repute of a fair dealer, and was a man of great buſineſſe in honourable imployment in the ſervice of his Country, and quit himſelf like a man of worth and valour, as a Captain, a Major, a Collonell and Major Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, after ſerved in Parliament, and a Commiſſioner of Cuſtomes with ſo much induſtry and fidelity, as a man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied with buſineſſe, that to ſpeak ingenuouſly, I know but few men that can and will take the pains which I dayly ſee him undergoe, being naturally inclin'd to go through with what he undertakes, and this with his impartiall dealing hath ſufficiently irritated many men that would be ready to worke him a diſpleaſure: but God who gave him a heart to act by a principle of grace and true love to piety, hath carried him on in his worke, that malice it ſelf hath not had any juſt charge againſt him.</p>
            <p>And as for the other Commiſſioners, if wiſdome her ſelf had been ſet a work curiouſly to ſearch, ſhe could not have found men more ſingle hearted, upright, fearing God and eſchewing evill, men that deſire in all good conſcience to diſcharge their duty to the truſt repoſed in them. And I dare ſay, it is beleeved by all that know them, they are ſuch, and I can with truth and boldneſſe affirme it, and add this to them all in generall, that diſcreeter, juſter, abler, and men ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording in one minde and judgement, with love and reſpect to one another and all with whom as to their imployment they have to do as Commiſſioners, never yet ſuch were known to me, and I am perſwaded it will be hard to finde ſuch an agreement for ſo long a time by any four men in the world, in ſo eminent an imployment.</p>
            <p>Yet <hi>Neceſſity</hi> ſtigmatizeth them with the blackeſt marks of infamy as grand obſtructers of the publick revenewes, vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:192174:9"/>of truſt, defrauders of the Common-wealth, concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the duty of Exciſe.</p>
            <p>And yet again, another charge for obſtructing the receipt, pag. 6. <hi>They conſtantly grant Sufferances.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's not true that they conſtantly grant them, but in one of theſe caſes following.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By way of exportation, and only on ſuch goods where the halfe ſubſidy is to be drawn back and the whole Exciſe, only for accommodation of trade that they may be ſhipped and not paſſe Graves-end untill a Cocket be paſſed, and the Exciſe officers have certified they are ſatisfied.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When Cuſtome is paid and Exciſe certified to be ſatisfied for ſmall parcels, ſufferances are granted to bring up the ſaid goods in. Wherries, which otherwiſe traders are obliged to do in Lighters.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For the landing Graff and bulky goods, as Deals. Maſts, Spars, Pitch, Tar, Hemp, &amp;c. which ever were granted, and without which Merchants could not trade in thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, the lawfull Keys, if four times as many, being too few to take up and ſtore the ſame.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Sufferances are granted to land ſuch goods as no Merchant comes to claime, and to put them inthe Common-wealths warehouſe till the Merchant comes to demand them, which goods are not delivered without a warrant paſſed by the Commiſſioners of the Cuſtomes, which they never paſſe till the Cuſtomes be firſt paid, and never ſuffer the ſame to be executed untill they have certificate from the Exciſe officer that Exciſe is ſatisfied.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And laſtly, Sufferances are granted for landing goods tranſported from other ports of this Nation to the Port of <hi>London,</hi> and they are either goods Exciſeable, or free from Exciſe, as Sea-coles, Corne, Butter, Cheefe, Wool, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>For ſuch goods as are Exciſeable there is never any Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances granted, untill firſt the Exciſe officers hand be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed; and theſe are the Sufferances this empty headed man makes ſuch adoe about, accuſing the Commiſſioners of Cuſtomes for granting ſufferances without any Exciſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:192174:10"/>officers hand ſubſcribed; when as they never grant any of the aforeſaid ſufferances except that for exportation and goods not Exciſeable, but when they have firſt granted a warrant, and they never grant a warrant but they firſt have the Exciſe officers hand to certifie he hath received ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and that this is the conſtant practiſe at the Cuſtome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe as is dayly manifeſted; and all this they are authorized to do by the Parliament, for avoiding unreaſonable incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences to the Merchants.</p>
            <p>And for the goods not liable to Exciſe, as Sea-coals, &amp;c. You cannot forget, if you have not quite loſt your memory, that about two years ſince, the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners of Exciſe deſired a conference with the Commiſſioners of Cuſtoms concerning ſufferances by them granted, where you would needs ſhew how ignorant you were in the buſineſſe you would pretend ſo much knowledg in, and did there ſputter out a deal of nonſenſe, inſomuch as your brethren were aſhamed of you, and like diſcreet men did informe you in good words, you underſtood not the thing you ſpake of: were not many officers of Cuſtomes and Exciſe witneſſes of your pertina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious cariage in managing that debate, and were much grieved that a Common-wealth abounding with many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent men of parts and integrity, ſhould be ſerved in ſo high an imployment by a ſupercilious conceited pragmatick buſibody, that pretends to finde holes in other mens coates, when he might have work enough to imploy more wit then the ſhallow pan of his brains can hold, in ſearching out the leaks whereby ſo much treaſure ſlips beſide the receipt of the Exciſe, and ſo begin reformation at home. But to proceed, after your wiſer brethren had perſwaded your imperiouſneſſe to admit of a debate between them and the Commiſſioners for Cuſtomes, it was concluded for goods Exciſeable from the Coaſt, that the ancient and uninterrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted way of ſufferances granted joyntly by the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Cuſtomes and Exciſe ſhould be continued, but as for this new device of your brain for ſuch an injunction for goods that owed no Exciſe, they all except your ſelf
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:192174:10"/>(wiſer in your own conceit then ſeven men that can render a reaſon) could ſee no cauſe for, yet you could not reſt with this, but about a moneth after your ſurvayour or deputy came to the Commiſſioners of Cuſtomes to let them know, it was expected that ſufferances for goods that owed no Exciſe, ſhould be ſigned by the ſurvayour or deputy for Exciſe, as well as by the Commiſſioners of Cuſtomes; whereupon the Commiſſioners of Cuſtomes readily compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (although they knew it uſeleſſe to the State) and gave order to their Clerks to prepare and order accordingly.</p>
            <p>But the Maſters trading to Newcaſtle, and other parts, refuſed to go to the Exciſe officers for any ſuch ſufferances, ſaying, they were Engliſh men and by law not enjoyned thereunto; and that thoſe things required were inovatious and troubleſome, and they could not write the bills well enough to pleaſe the Exciſe officers; and therefore were neceſſitated to get the Deputy or ſome other Clerks of Exciſe to write, and ſo on every entry to pay for two lines writing 6. <hi>d.</hi> or 4. <hi>d.</hi> which upon ſo many thouſand entries would amount unto a vaſt ſum of money, meerly cheated out of their purſes, and thereupon the Ship-maſters reſolved to land their goods upon tender of their Cockets unto the Commiſſioners of Cuſtomes, as by law they were injoyned; which the Commiſſioners well weighing, and knowing by law no more was injoyned, did deſire the Survayor of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe to acquaint the Commiſſioners of Exciſe therewith, that except they did ſhew reaſon to the contrary, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of Cuſtomes ought and would proceed to grant ſufferances by themſelves for all goods not Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſeable.</p>
            <p>But the Survayor of Exciſe anſwered, that the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners of Exciſe did adhere to their former reſolution, whereupon the Commiſſioners of Cuſtomes did again con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with the Commiſſioners of Exciſe, and found but one of them ingaged with the Deputy, and the reſt declared they were put upon it by the Deputy. And I am perſwaded it was only <hi>Neceſſity</hi> put him upon it, and had it been caried
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:192174:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>on their parts, it would have made a good revenue for themſelves by a multitude of ſix-pennies or groats, which it ſeems they had projected to have received: a meer oppreſſion and exaction as ever was thruſt upon a people.</p>
            <p>Which cauſed the Commiſſioners of Cuſtomes to ſend for the Surveyor or Deputy of Exciſe <hi>T. L.</hi> and plainly tell him, that they now diſcerned the reaſon of his ſtrong en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours for this innovation being of no uſe but to vex the ſhip-maſters, and traders, and bring money to his office, and ſupply <hi>Neceſſity.</hi> And therefore this goes ſo neer the heart of this Miſer, that he complaines <hi>pag.</hi> the 6. <hi>lin.</hi> 10. <hi>And one of them did ſharpely rebuke the Surveyor of Exciſe for diſcovering their miſdemeanors to the Commiſſioners of Exciſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But conſider this jugling <hi>Neceſſity</hi> had urged the Surveyor or Deputy <hi>T. L.</hi> upon a foul miſdemeanour, for which he was worthily reprehended by the Commiſſioners of Cuſtomes. And now this ſhitlecock cries whore firſt, and layes miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanours upon the Commiſſioners of Cuſtomes; who, as I have ſaid, are men of unquaſtionable integrity and ability to manage their truſt; yet he hath the impudence to do what he can to bluſh their reputation: But they are above the aire of his ſtinking breath, nor can his black mouth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpot their innocence, and thoſe ſharp arrowes his bitter words, will retort upon his own ſoul either to humble or terrifie him.</p>
            <p>And yet he hath one envenomed dart which he would ſtick in their very hearts, and charges the Commiſſioners of Cuſtomes that they <hi>have unduely maintained perſons detected of defrauding the Exciſe;</hi> the Devill himſelfe would have been aſhamed to have printed ſuch a lie, it's true he is the Father of lies, and skilfull in making lies, but he was ſo carefull in delivering his oracles that they ſhould have ſome colour of truth in them, and would ſo contrive his anſwers that whatſoever the event was, yet he would ſhew ſo much wit as not to be found in a lie; but though you cannot out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wit him, you will out-lie him, take heed he be not too wiſe for you at laſt; how can you thinke ever to be beleeved by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:192174:11"/>honeſt men? they ſay, what is bred in the bone, will never out of the fleſh, your firſt trade in drawing Chancery bils wherein men take liberty to lie at large, hath begotten in you ſuch a cuſtome that you cannot leave it.</p>
            <p>You might have done well to have named ſome of thoſe detected perſons, that ſo there might have been ſome colour of truth, and that Knaves might be known from honeſt men; but you throw your dirt at randome, and care not who you daube, and deprave a great many better men then your ſelfe, and till you make good your charge, they cannot but think as bad of you as you write of them.</p>
            <p>But what perſons did your wiſdome ever detect? I can inſtance many diſcoveries that have been made by the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and inſight of the Commiſſioners of Cuſtomes, of ſeveral frauds whereby the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> was baſely cheated, as that of counterfeit warrants, which all your skill could not finde out although it was chiefly in defrauding the Exciſe, whereby the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> was wronged of many thouſand pounds, and was but newly begun to be practiſed in the Cuſtomes, but the Commiſſioners there diſcovered and found out thoſe unworthy officers of your putting in, or continuance.</p>
            <p>Witneſſe alſo that notable combination of your dearly beloved <hi>Pratt</hi> with <hi>Ludlow</hi> and <hi>Welden</hi> Cuſtome officers, what deceitfull practiſes were by them diſcovered: I might inſtance in many more, wherein by the prudence and vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant inſpection of the Commiſſioners of Cuſtomes, ſuch perſons have been detected, and impriſoned, and caſt out, and made uncapable of any preferment where they have to doe, and yet this pertinacious peece of confidence ſayes, they maintain perſons detected, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>They ſay that the receiver is as bad as the theef, if you knew this why did you not reveal it? if you were privy to ſuch unjuſt practiſes, you did not well to conceale them; how have you diſcharged your truſt for theſe many years? why did you not complain before? the law upon convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on would puniſh ſuch with impriſonment, and forfeiture of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:192174:12"/>double value of the goods that the Exciſe amounted unto, and could your fellows be all this while ſilent in a matter of ſo great concernment? and now as if on a ſudda'n your conſcience were awakened, you ſhew your ſelf to do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be talked of, as if you were the only man that did all buſineſſe, and they all ſtand for ciphers; But they know, and I know, and all the world (that have to do with you) knows you to be a ſhatterbraind, ratle-headed man, altogether unfit and unworthy the place you hold, and thoſe that act with you, know my words to be true, and would be able to give a better accompt of their buſineſſe, if you were out. I have heard and beleeve it, that when you crept into this imployment, you were preſently ſo eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that having the luck (as you know who hath the beſt) to be named firſt in the Act of Parliament, you began to look big, and would take the firſt place, and thought your ſelf the beſt man; and it ſeems you perſiſt in this conceit: your brethren like wiſe men follow their own buſineſſe endeavouring to diſcharge their truſt, whileſt you neglect to ſweep your own door; are raking in other mens ſinkes, and hope to domineer every where as you do in your office, to put in kindred into imployments, and will ſuffer nought to be done without applications in private be made to your worſhip, and be it right or wrong, nothing muſt be done but according to your own ſenſe.</p>
            <p>But the laſt, though not the leaſt thing that troubles <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> is a Reducement; and this his fear hath occaſioned all that he hath written before: for here he ſhewes <hi>pag. 6.</hi> what is his main drift, <hi>In caſe Reducement of Exciſe to the Cuſtome be adjudged advantagious to the Common-wealth, may not not both receipts ſo reduced be managed by perſons verſed in both imployments, that have ſuffered in their eſtates for the Common-wealth, and are of approved integrity, at the ſalary of three halfe pence poundage?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Poor man, thy qualfications have undone thee, it will be to great a work for your brains, nor are you capable by your own words: you ſay well that there ſhould be reſpect had
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:192174:12"/>to men that have ſuffered for the Comm-wealth; but all that know you can tell you have been a gainer not a loſer by the Common-wealth, having had divers good warme places, wherein you have not been wanting to make the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt; and having learned to make advantages of places, you are now loath to be left out, and then you would imagine your ſelf into the opinion of good men, that you are one that ſeeks the welfare of the Nation. And (good ſoul) art grieved to ſee the publick treaſure ſo miſcarry, and like <hi>Abſolom,</hi> O that I were Judge in <hi>Iſrael!</hi> So, if I had the management of both receipts of Cuſtome and Exciſe! and ſo by glavering words and ſcraping officious attendances, you truſt to get into an Office which will require a more able, ſolider, and better qualified man, then one ſo low puzed as you ſet your ſelf out to be; you ſee <hi>Abſalom</hi> he had a deſigne or end he aimed at in his flattering the people, and ſo have you, and for ought I know it might be better for the Common-wealth you had <hi>Abſoloms</hi> end, then your own; but you hope to ſpeed by offering your ſervice cheaper then others will do it for; but I hope all wiſe men know, better give 2 <hi>s.</hi> * a day to a workman, then 12 <hi>d.</hi> a day to a bungler: can it be imagined that it is good to truſt two ſuch receipts in the hands of thoſe who is like to bring a Noble to 9 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have many more things to write, but I ſhall reſerve them till I come to rejoyne with you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Jeremiah Wattes.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
